Welcome back.
Now that we've completed our discussion of leukemias,
we can now address lymph nodes.
And the first topic that we're going to discuss
is lymphadenopathy.
Lymphadenopathy refers to enlarged lymph nodes.
And it's important to note that lymphadenopathy
can be painful or painless.
Painful lymphadenopathy is usually seen
when there's acute infection
and the lymph node is draining that region of infection.
For example, let's say that the patient
has a strep throat.
The lymph nodes in the neck will then be enlarged
and they will be painful.
So that would be called painful lymphadenopathy.
At the same time, it is also possible
to develop a painless lymphadenopathy.
And the differential diagnosis
for painless lymphadenopathy includes chronic inflammation.
So for example, autoimmune diseases
often have painless lymphadenopathy associated with them.
Metastatic carcinoma.
If carcinoma spreads to a local lymph node,
it's usually painless enlargement of the lymph node that occurs.
For example, if a woman has breast cancer
and it spreads to the axillary lymph nodes,
the axillary lymph nodes become enlarged
and that's usually painless.
And the third circumstance in which we can get
painless lymphadenopathy is lymphoma.
So when we think about painless lymphadenopathy,
we really have three major differential diagnoses in our mind.
Chronic inflammation, metastatic carcinoma, or lymphoma.
We're going to cover lymphoma in much more detail in just a few slides.
However, when we have a reactive lymphadenopathy,
meaning that the lymph node is big due to some chronic inflammation or reactive process,
it is important to note that there is going to be hyperplasia of differing
regions of the lymph node depending on the underlying etiology.
For example, if the patient has rheumatoid arthritis,
it's classic for there to be expansion of the follicles
and it's this expansion of the follicles that would lead to enlargement of the lymph node.
Similarly, in early HIV, there's also expansion of the follicles
and again, it's expansion of the follicles that results in the generalized lymphadenopathy
that's often seen in early HIV.
Now recall that HIV infects CD4-positive cells
and of course, the most important and classic infection would be of the CD4-positive T cells.
However, the cells in the follicle, the follicular dendritic cells,
they also are CD4-positive.
And that's why you see this follicular hyperplasia in early HIV.
The paracortex is the region where the T cells live
and so it's pretty straightforward for us to understand
that with viral infection, the paracortex would become expanded
and it's expansion of the paracortex that leads to lymphadenopathy.
The classic example would be infectious mononucleosis.
Recall that in infectious mononucleosis,
an EBV infection results in enlargement of the lymph nodes
and that's going to be due to paracortical expansion of the lymph node.
And then finally, we can see enlargement of the lymph node
due to expansion of the region where the histiocytes live.
And of course, the histiocytes live deep in the sinus
in the medulla of the lymph node.
And this is classically seen when there is a lymph node
that is draining a region of cancer.
Let's say that a woman has breast cancer
and there are some lymph nodes that are draining that region.
Well, it would be classic to see sinus histiocytosis
in those lymph nodes.
Now, of course, the cancer hasn't gone to the lymph node in this case,
but this lymph node is simply becoming reactive
because it's draining a region of cancer.
And so that's another classic cause of lymphadenopathy.
Here's a picture of a lymph node,
just to remind ourselves of the normal architecture.
Up here would be the cortex.
Underneath the cortex is the paracortex
and in this region is the medulla.
Now, of course, the cortex is where the B cells live.
The paracortex is where the T cells live.
And the medulla, can you see these lighter pink areas here?
This is where the sinus histiocytes live.
And so these are the three major regions of the lymph node.
Of course, we'd see follicular expansion in the cortex
with rheumatoid arthritis and early HIV.
We'd see expansion of the paracortex with viral infections.
And again, we would see expansion of the medullary region
when we had a lymph node that was draining a region of cancer.
Now, I put this here in your text and in this discussion
because it's often that examiners like to ask
about which region of the lymph node is expanded
based on a particular etiology.
So that's a relatively short section.
And now we're going to move into lymphoma.
And basically, the very first principle that I'd like to establish
is that lymphoma is a neoplastic proliferation of lymphoid cells
that forms a mass, lymph, i.e. lymphoid cells,
oma that forms a mass.
And that's what gives it its name of lymphoma.
Now, lymphoma can arise within the lymph node.
And that makes sense because that's where lymphocytes normally live.
But it can also arise within extranodal tissues
outside of the lymph node.
When we think about lymphoma generally,
we should remind ourselves that lymphoma can be divided
into non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, which is the more common type,
and Hodgkin's lymphoma, which is still relatively common.
We will talk in more detail about Hodgkin's lymphoma
a little later on.
And so at this point, what I'm going to do
is simply focus on the non-Hodgkin's lymphomas.
When we think about the non-Hodgkin's lymphoma,
we can classify them based on several parameters.
These include cell type, for example, B cell versus T cell.
Cell size, for example, small cells or intermediate,
B cells or large cells.
Pattern of growth, for example,
do the cells grow in a diffuse sheet
or do they form follicles, just as an example.
Expression of surface markers, in particular,
which would help us to determine
whether the cells are B cells or T cells.
And also cytogenetic translocations.
Now, classically, when you think about non-Hodgkin's lymphoma,
there have been multiple classification schemes.
And I don't want to go into the nitty-gritty in details,
but I'll just simply tell you that
I think about Hodgkin's lymphoma
in a rather simplistic manner.
It's probably not the most accurate way
if you were a hematopathologist or a hematologist,
but I do think that it is an easy way
to understand a very difficult concept.
And so what we're going to do is
I'm going to sort of base my division
of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma on cell size.
Now, in our discussion, we're going to be focusing
on the B cell types of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma,
which are the vast majority of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
So we're going to base it on cell size,
and part of that discussion will also be based
on pattern of growth.
But this will become clear just in a moment.
So let's go to a whiteboard and remind ourselves
that really when you think about cell size,
lymphocytes, when they're neoplastic,
can be small, can be intermediate, or can be large.
When the lymphocytes are small,
we would think about those as well-differentiated.
In other words, small lymphocytes that are neoplastic
are well-differentiated.
They look just like very similar to normal lymphocytes.
So they're going to do, on occasion, when they grow,
they're going to grow in the patterns
in which normal lymphocytes grow.
Let's go back and remind ourselves
of the normal lymph node.
Remember that we're focusing on B cells,
and so the normal B area of the lymph node
is the cortex, and in the cortex,
you have something called the follicle.
That's the follicle.
And around the follicle is the mantle.
It's a dark area that surrounds the follicle.
This is called the mantle.
And then, outside of the mantle, on occasion,
not always, but on occasion,
we'll actually have generation
of something called the margin.
So these are the normal zones of the B area
of the lymph node, follicle, mantle, and margin.
And when we think about cells that are small,
that are neoplastic,
they basically produce structures
that are very similar to the normal lymph node.
So we can have a follicular lymphoma
that's going to produce a bunch of follicle-like structures.
We can have expansion of the mantle zone
by neoplastic cells,
which is called a mantle cell lymphoma.
Or we can have expansion of the marginal zone
by neoplastic cells,
which is called a marginal zone lymphoma.
And these are the three key lymphomas
that arise from small neoplastic B cells.
There is a fourth one,
which I'm not going to discuss here,
which we've already discussed,
and that's small lymphocytic lymphoma.
And recall that that is when
CLL involves the lymph nodes.
But basically, here I'm going to focus
on follicular lymphoma, mantle cell lymphoma,
and marginal zone lymphoma.
Follicular lymphoma is a neoplastic proliferation
of small B cells.
Those B cells would be CD20 positive.
CD20 is a key marker for B cells.
And these small B cells are going to make
follicle-like nodules,
hence the name follicular lymphoma.
Clinically, it presents in late adulthood
and usually with painless lymphadenopathy.
Now, lymphadenopathy refers to
enlargement of the lymph nodes.
And these patients will have generalized
lymphadenopathy throughout the body
that is painless.
Here is a picture of follicular lymphoma.
And what we can appreciate here
is that we're dealing with a lymph node.
And we see that the lymph node
basically contains dozens of these follicles.
So these lymphocytes are making follicle-like structures,
hence the term follicular lymphoma.
One of the important findings in follicular lymphoma
is that it is driven by a translocation of 1418.
Important to remember and very high yield
that what's happening here
is that if this is 14,
normally in a B cell,
on chromosome 14 at this particular locus
is immunoglobulin heavy chain.
And what translocates with immunoglobulin heavy chain
in follicular lymphoma
is a gene called BCL2.
BCL2 happens to be on chromosome 18.
And so this 1418 translocation
pushes BCL2 into the position
where immunoglobulin heavy chain was once sitting.
Now, immunoglobulin heavy chain gene
is a highly active gene in B cells.
And so BCL2, when it gets translocated here,
becomes highly active and becomes overexpressed.
How does that create a follicular lymphoma?
Let's recall that BCL2,
its role is to stabilize the mitochondrial membrane.
And by stabilizing the mitochondrial membrane,
it prohibits cytochrome C
from leaking from the mitochondria
into the cytoplasm.
And that blocks apoptosis.
Most cells in the human body,
they express BCL2
because you don't want apoptosis to occur
and you want to hide away cytochrome C.
However, in the follicle of the lymph node,
that's the one place,
that's the particular place in the human body
where you actually want apoptosis to occur.
Why?
Well, what's normally going on in the follicle?
In the follicle,
you get somatic hypermutation of the B cells.
The B cells come in
and they are challenged by antigen
and they undergo somatic hypermutation
to see whether they can bind or produce antibodies
that are going to bind against that antigen.
If they pass somatic hypermutation,
they then go from the germinal center
and they can then participate in inflammation.
However, if they fail somatic hypermutation,
which the vast majority of B cells do,
then they undergo apoptosis.
And when they undergo apoptosis,
that allows them to die.
Now imagine if there's a translocation of the B cells
so that BCL2 is overexpressed,
then those cells that should have died in the follicle
actually won't be able to die.
And that's then going to result
in a follicular lymphoma.
So because we need apoptosis in the follicle
and we aren't able to undergo apoptosis
due to the high BCL2,
a follicular lymphoma will develop.
And that's what I'm highlighting here in your slide
where I say that it's driven by a 14-18 translocation
and that involves BCL2 on chromosome 18
which translocates to the immunoglobulin heavy chain locus
on chromosome 14.
Again, overexpression of BCL2
then inhibits apoptosis.
These patients are relatively asymptomatic
and they live for a long period of time
with this disease.
Treatment is usually reserved for patients
who are symptomatic
and one way by which we could treat
is to give low-dose chemotherapy
another way would be to give
a drug called rituximab
which is an anti-CD20 antibody.
So this is another way
by which we could treat follicular lymphoma.
The complication of follicular lymphoma
is that it can progress
to a diffuse large B-cell lymphoma.
So over time
it could actually pick up additional mutations
resulting in a diffuse large B-cell lymphoma
and this would present as an enlarging lymph node.
Now recall that patients with follicular lymphoma
they have generalized lymphadenopathy
where they have multiple lymph nodes
in their body that are enlarged.
If all of a sudden
one of those lymph nodes
begins to become further enlarged,
begins to grow more,
then we think about progression
to diffuse large B-cell lymphoma.
It is very important
for the purposes of both clinics
as well as board exams
to distinguish follicular hyperplasia
from follicular lymphoma.
Now what do I mean by that?
If a patient gets an infection
it is possible
that they could get hyperplasia
of the follicles
just as a result of that infection.
And so we need to
when we see a bunch of follicles
within a lymph node
we need to be able to distinguish
is this due to follicular lymphoma
which is neoplastic
or is this simply a reaction
to an infection?
Now how could we do that?
Well number one
when we have follicular lymphoma
there will be disruption
of the lymph node architecture.
What do I mean by that?
Well I'm going to take you back
a couple slides
to this picture
which I had drawn you here
and let's look at this lymph node again.
When we look at this lymph node
what we see
is that there are follicles
throughout the entire lymph node
and we don't see any other structures.
So these follicles
have basically taken over
or disrupted
the normal lymph node architecture
and that's an indication
that we're dealing
with follicular lymphoma.
If this was a follicular hyperplasia
in response to an infection
we would see expansion
of the follicles
but all of the follicles
would be present
in the cortex
where the follicles
normally live.
The fact that these follicles
are destroying the lymph node
and going deep
into the lymph node
is an indication
that we may be dealing
with a follicular lymphoma.
The second important feature
concerning the distinction
between hyperplasia
and lymphoma
is a lack of tingible body macrophages
in the germinal center.
This image here
is meant to highlight that.
Now let's remind ourselves
that when we have infection
then we're going to get
a follicular hyperplasia
and that follicular hyperplasia
occurs because B cells
are coming into the follicle
they are undergoing
somatic hypermutation
in the follicle
and as a result
of somatic hypermutation
many of them are dying.
Now if the B cells
in the follicle
are truly undergoing
somatic hypermutation
and dying via apoptosis
then recall
that the response
to apoptosis
at the very end
is that the macrophages
come in
and they clean up
the dead cells.
And so if we have
a follicle
that is reacting
to infection
we should see
a ton of macrophages
present within
the germinal center.
And that's what
these little white spaces
here represent
within this germinal center.
So why don't I take you
back a step
and show you
that this is
the germinal center.
This darker blue area
here is actually
the mantle
surrounding the germinal center
and within this germinal center
we see these white spaces
which indicate
that macrophages
are present
and are eating
the debris
of apoptotic cells.
These macrophages
are also called
tingible body macrophages
and they indicate
again
that apoptosis
is actively occurring
within the germinal center.
Now let's contrast
that against
follicular lymphoma.
Here's the follicle
of follicular lymphoma.
Do you see
any tingible body macrophages
in that follicle?
The answer is no.
We don't have
those nice
tingible body macrophages
in the center
of that follicle
and that's because
these cells
are not undergoing
apoptosis.
They have undergone
a 14-18 translocation.
BCL2 is overexpressed
and the overexpression
of BCL2
is actually blocking
apoptosis
in these cells.
And that's an important
point concerning
follicular lymphoma.
A third important point
concerning follicular lymphoma
is the expression
of BCL2
in the follicles.
The vast majority
of cells
in the human body
they express BCL2
and that's because
you don't want
those cells
to undergo apoptosis.
However,
in the follicle,
in a normal follicle
in you and I
there would be
no expression
of BCL2
because you want
to turn BCL2 off
to allow
for apoptosis.
But if there is
expression of BCL2
that would indicate
that we're dealing
with a follicular lymphoma.
The final way
by which we can make
this distinction
is monoclonality.
Recall that if we have
a reactive proliferation
of lymphocytes
and this goes back
to our discussions
of neoplasia,
if you have a reactive
proliferation of lymphocytes
it would be
polyclonal.
And if we have
a neoplastic proliferation
of lymphocytes
it would be monoclonal.
And of course
clonality is gauged
in B cells
by looking at
the ratio
of kappa to lambda
light chain.
In a polyclonal
reactive proliferation
the ratio
would be 3 to 1
whereas in neoplasia
the ratio
would be disrupted
for example
classically
on an examination
20 to 1
or 25 to 1.
So that is
follicular lymphoma.
Now we come
to mantle cell lymphoma
and mantle cell lymphoma
is when you have
a neoplastic proliferation
of small B cells
obviously CD20 positive
that expand
the mantle zone.
This clinically
also presents
in late adulthood
and also presents
with generalized
painless lymphadenopathy.
Now
when you have
this type of tumor
one of the classic
descriptions on examination
is that the examiners
could tell you
that there is
a neoplastic
proliferation of cells
that expands
the region
immediately adjacent
to the follicle.
If you have
a tumor
that expands
the region
immediately adjacent
to the follicle
that region
is obviously
the mantle
and so that
would be
a mantle cell
lymphoma.
So that's
a nice way
that examiners
might try
to describe
the tumor.
This tumor
is driven
by an 11-14
translocation.
Well what's
on 14?
Immunoglobulin
heavy chain.
What gets
translocated
to that spot?
Cyclin D.
That's the key
gene
that's going
to drive
the production
of mantle cell
lymphoma.
Now recall
that Cyclin D
is a cell cycle
regulator.
It helps
the cell
to go from
G1
to S phase
and the way
that it does
it is by
phosphorylating
proteins.
So a high
level of Cyclin D
would actually
phosphorylate
the regulators
allowing the
cell to go
from G1
to S phase
and this is
important
for examination
purposes.
You need to know
that Cyclin D
causes the cell
to go from
the G1
to S phase
and this is
a key
translocation
in mantle cell
lymphoma.
The third
lymphoma
that would
produce
structures
similar to
the normal
lymph node
is a
marginal zone
lymphoma.
So what
is the
marginal zone?
The marginal
zone is
that region
which is
outside
of the mantle.
Here's
the lymph node
again.
This is
the follicle.
Outside
of the follicle
would be
the mantle
and outside
of the mantle
would be
the margin.
And so
we could
develop a tumor
that expands
the marginal
zone
and that's
called
a marginal
zone
lymphoma.
Again
it's usually
due to
neoplastic
B cells
that are
going to
be
CD20
positive.
Important
to know
that this
type of
lymphoma
is associated
with chronic
inflammatory
states.
This kind
of goes
back a
little
bit
to
normal
immunology
because
remember
that
most
lymph nodes
don't have
a marginal
zone.
The marginal
zone is
actually
formed
by when
there
is
activation
of the
cells
through
the
germinal
center.
And so
when
cells
go
into
the
germinal
center
and get
activated
because
of for
example
chronic
inflammation
that's
when the
margin
zone
would be
classically
seen
I should
say
when
there's
chronic
inflammatory
states.
So what
are some
associated
disorders?
In
Hashimoto's
thyroiditis
patients
can develop
a marginal
zone
lymphoma
as a
complication
years
later.
In
Sjogren
syndrome
as I've
already
described
in the
immunology
lectures
we can
develop
a
complication
of
marginal
zone
lymphoma
and the
idea
here
would be
that
the
patient
presents
with
unilateral
enlargement
of the
parotid
years
into
her
Sjogren
syndrome
and then
another
classic
one
is
H.
pylori
gastritis
now
in
H.
pylori
gastritis
what
happens
is that
you get
a
marginal
zone
lymphoma
in
mucosal
sites
and
that's
also
called
a
maltoma
and again
the
gastric
maltoma
in the
mucosa
of the
stomach
can possibly
regress
if the
H.
pylori
is
treated
and
so
maltoma
mucosa
associated
lymphoid
tissue
OMA
mass
is
one
of the
subtypes
of
marginal
zone
lymphoma
now
that
concludes
our
discussion
of the
small
cell
B-cell
lymphomas
that
mimic
normal
structure
of the
lymph
node
and
so
we're
going to
move
now
to
a
tumor
in
which
we
have
B-cells
that
are
CD20
positive
there
is
an
association
with
EBV
classically
this
tumor
presents
as
an
extra
nodal
mass
in
a
child
or
young
adult
there
are
two
forms
it's
the
African
form
which
produces
a jaw
mass
and
there's
a sporadic
form
which
involves
the
abdomen
one
of
the
ways
by
which
examiners
like
to
and
then
you
could
potentially
be
asked
well
where
would
the
for
example
where
would
the
sporadic
form
arise
and
the
sporadic
form
arises
more
commonly
in
the
abdomen
African
form
more
commonly
arises
in
the
jaw
very
important
to know
about
these
tumors
that
they're
driven
by
translocations
of
C-mic
is
present
on
chromosome
the
most
common
translocation
is
an
8-14
translocation
in
this
particular
case
C-mic
gets
translocated
to
the
immunoglobulin
heavy
chain
locus
on
and
that
results
in
overexpression
of
C-mic
now
is
a
nuclear
regulator
that
activates
multiple
genes
necessary
for
promotion
of
growth
and
so
when
you
have
a
lot
of
C-mic
you're
going
to
have
a
lot
of
growth
and
that
is
then
going
to
drive
production
of
the
tumor
so
most
important
to
recognize
that
has
a
very
high
mitotic
rate
and
that
rapid
growth
results
in
a
starry
sky
appearance
on
histology
let me
explain
that
a
little
further
here's
the
histology
and
these
cells
all
of
these
circular
blue
cells
these
represent
the
tumor
and
so
they
call
this
the
sky
blue
represents
the
sky
and
then
here
some
of
the
cells
are
turning
over
so
quickly
that
they're
actually
dying
and
these
are
macrophages
i.e.
tingible
body
macrophages
that are
present
within
the tumor
and
are
eating
away
the
cells
as
they
die
they're
growing
so
fast
that
they
die
so
that
is
the
star
so
the
blue
represents
the
sky
and
this
white
area
represents
the
star
and
the
classic
again
description
is
a
starry
sky
appearance
so
that
takes
care
of
the
intermediate
sized
lymphoma
of
B
cells
now
we
come
to
the
lymphoma
in
which
there
are
large
B
cells
and
this
is
called
diffuse
large
B
cell
lymphoma
diffuse
it
doesn't
produce
follicles
it
doesn't
produce
a
margin
it
doesn't
produce
a
mantle
it
grows
diffusely
large
the
cells
are
large
B
the
cells
are
B
cells
and
hence
they're
CD20
positive
and
of
course
this
is
a
lymphoma
so
that's
the
summary
of
diffuse
large
B
cell
lymphoma
it's
the
most
common
form
of
non
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
and
it's
clinically
very
aggressive
it
would
make
sense
that
it's
clinically
aggressive
because
it's
not
well
differentiated
it doesn't
look like
normal
structure
it doesn't
have
small
B
cells
and
so
because
it's
poorly
differentiated
we would
expect
it to
be
clinically
aggressive
now
diffuse
large
B
cell
lymphoma
can
arise
sporadically
or
it
can
arise
from
transformation
of
follicular
lymphoma
and
I've
already
explained
that
in
detail
when
we
talked
about
follicular
lymphoma
this
tumor
presents
in
late
adulthood
usually
as
an
enlarging
lymph
node
or
as
an
extranodal
mass
once
you've
understood
non-Hodgkin's
lymphoma
you can
now
then
move
to
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
and
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
is
not
too
difficult
to
understand
basically
the
notion
in
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
is
that
instead
of
having
a
whole
mass
of
malignant
cells
so
for
example
in
a
non-Hodgkin's
lymphoma
the
entire
mass
is
composed
of
malignant
cells
well
in
a
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
you
don't
have
a
big
mass
of
malignant
cells
instead
you
have
rare
neoplastic
cells
called
Reed-Sternberg
cells
and
those
Reed-Sternberg
cells
secrete
cytokines
that
draw
in
other
inflammatory
cells
which
then
results
in
production
of
a
mass
and
so
the
key
hallmark
of
a
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
is
a
Reed-Sternberg
cell
the
Reed-Sternberg
cell
is a
large
B cell
classically
with a
multi-lobed
nucleus
and a
prominent
nucleolus
and often
and usually
most commonly
they are
CD15
and CD30
positive
notice that
there is
no
CD20
expression
here
although
it's
clearly
a
B cell
they are
CD15
and CD30
positive
now
here's
a picture
of a
Reed-Sternberg
cell
I put one
here in
the center
this
is a
large
cell
it
has
a
multi-lobed
nucleus
here's
one
lobe
here's
another
lobe
we can
clearly
see
this
nucleolus
darker
purple
area
and
this
kind
of
gives
the
appearance
of
owl
eyes
and
so
it's
also
called
an
owl
eyed
nucleus
so
that's
a
Reed-Sternberg
cell
now
notice
that
there's
one
Reed-Sternberg
cell
but
it's
the
Reed-Sternberg
cell
along
with
all
the
reactive
cells
that's
actually
producing
the
mass
and
so
that
is
going
to
be
classic
for
a
Hodgkin's
lymphoma
now
in the
Reed-Sternberg
cells
they secrete
cytokines
and when
they secrete
cytokines
that's going
to result
in a few
things
number
one
a subset
of these
patients
can present
with B
symptoms
B
are like
fever
chills
and night
sweats
and it's
actually due
to the
cytokines
being produced
are going
to attract
lymphocytes
plasma
cells
macrophages
and eosinophils
which are
then going
to cause
the actual
mass
to form
so the
bulk
of the
tumor
the bulk
of the
mass
in this
disorder
is actually
reactive
cells
also
fibrosis
may be
present
and you'll
see why
that's
important
in a
moment
as I've
already
stated
the
reactive
inflammatory
cells
make up
the bulk
of the
tumor
and they
also
form
the basis
for
classification
so that
the subtypes
of Hodgkin's
lymphoma
include
nodular
sclerosis
this is
the most
common
and I'll
explain it
in more
detail
in a
moment
there's
a
lymphocyte
rich
variant
where
there's
a
ton
of
lymphocytes
that are
associated
with the
reed-sternberg
cell
there's
a
mixed
cellularity
variant
where
there's
mixed
cell
type
that's
associated
with
the
reed-sternberg
cell
especially
eosinophils
and there's
a
lymphocyte
depleted
variant
which
actually
has
minimal
lymphocytes
associated
with the
reed-sternberg
cell
the most
common
subtype
as I've
already
explained
is nodular
sclerosis
subtype
the classic
presentation
in nodular
sclerosis
subtype
is that
the patient
has an
enlarging
neck
lymph node
or an
enlarging
mediastinal
lymph node
and is
usually a
young
female
biopsy
is then
performed
and the
biopsy
reveals
a lymph
node
that is
divided
by broad
bands of
fibrosis
and this
is the
classic
histology
on low
power
this
is a
picture
of a
lymph
node
and you
can
see
that
there
is
broad
pink
bands
of
fibrosis
as I'm
outlining
here
and these
broad
pink
bands
of
fibrosis
are
cutting
the
lymph
node
into
these
nodules
and so
that's
nodular
sclerosis
subtype
remember
that the
word
sclerosis
just
means
hard
and
it's
hard
because
it's
got
all
this
fibrotic
tissue
within
it
at
the
same
time
one
of
the
classic
findings
on
histology
is
that
the
reed-sternberg
cells
in this
particular
subtype
often
sit
in
these
big
open
spaces
so
notice
that
we've
got
this
big
open
space
with
a
reed-sternberg
cell
in it
another
big
open
space
with
a
reed-sternberg
cell
in it
and so
these
spaces
look
like
lakes
and
so
they're
given
the
name
lacunar
cells
and
lacunar
cells
are
a
special
kind
not necessarily
super
common
and
it's
often
difficult
to remember
them
but
I'll
just
tell
you
a
few
important
principles
number
one
the
lymphocyte
rich
has
the
best
prognosis
number
two
the
lymphocyte
depleted
has
the
worst
prognosis
so
the
more
lymphocytes
the
better
less
the
lymphocytes
worse
when
and
very
important
to
know
for
examination
purposes
that
those
abundant
eosinophils
are being
called in
by
IL5
so
the
reed-sternberg
cell
is
overproducing
cytokines
for example
IL5
and it's
that draws
in the
eosinophils
in these
patients
there may
also be
an
eosinophilia
where they
have extra
eosinophils
in the
blood
and that's
also due
to increased
IL5
production
by the
reed-sternberg
cells
and that
closes off
our
discussion
of
lymphoma
not too
difficult
if you
just
keep
sort
of
the
big
picture
in
mind
as
you
go
through
them
our
next
discussion
will